<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Teebox Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-19T13:57:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[andy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Self Diagnosis - What does you clubface say about you?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/16/self-diagnosis-what-does-you-clubface-say-about-you/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-16T22:04:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/16/self-diagnosis-what-does-you-clubface-say-about-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;ve pored over the instructional section in every golf magazine, worked hard on your swing in the living room, and you’re ready for 18 holes this weekend with your buddies. But standing on the 10th tee, five shots over your handicap, it seems like everyone has an opinion on what exactly is going wrong. Ninety blows later and no matter what you tried, PGA Tour glory seems farther away than ever.</p>

<p>The authenticity of your buddies&#8217; tips are always under question, and these remarks and quick fixes rarely hit the mark. Want to get your golfing mojo back? Throw away the magazines, stop listening to your mates, and take control of your game by understanding the physics behind your shots. Quick fixes and clichés simply don&rsquo;t cut it anymore.</p>

<p>For simplicity’s sake, let’s set the record straight on one important matter; the face angle at impact is the main factor in determining your shot’s starting line and your golfing gratification. If the face is pointing left, the ball starts left. Don&rsquo;t believe us? Test it yourself. Grab a putter, cut across the ball, and keep the face open. Watch as the start line closely corresponds to the face angle at impact rather than the club path–which was the convention eons ago. Looking at both the face angle and club path at impact is key to deciphering the problems with your wayward shots and keeping your PGA Tour dreams alive.</p>

<p>So how is this going to help me make the cut, you ask? Lets look at a shot that haunts our nightmares. Starting left of the target and curving violently to the right, it’s the dreaded pull-slice. The shot starts left as the face is pointing left at impact, and due to the path of the club pointing further left than the face, the ball curves to the right.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/face-angle-relative-to-path.png"></p>

<p>If the face is open relative to the path by 0.5 to 20 degrees, the ball will always curve to the right with some spin. And what if the face is closed relative to the path? You guessed it, the ball curves to the left. It&rsquo;s really that simple.</p>

<p>Fixing the slice has been likened to squaring the circle (a mathematical impossibility), but remove the stigma around the shot and the solution is fundamentally simple. First, check your starting line. If it&rsquo;s anything other than straight down the center, check your clubface at setup. Tweak the face open a couple of degrees if the ball is starting left. You might be tempted to close the face at setup if the ball is starting right, but be warned, it&rsquo;s a slippery slope. Ensure the face is absolutely square and nothing more. Now give it a swing.</p>

<p>Are your shots starting straighter? Great, you&rsquo;re halfway there. Now you just need the club path pointing further right than the clubface for that PGA Tour power draw.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/face-angle-relative-to-path-draw.png"></p>

<p>Here are some common pro-approved moves that you can use to groove that in-to-out swing path:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Square the shoulders during the setup position. You&rsquo;d be surprised at how many of us have our shoulders pointing left at setup. Feel as though they are pointing to the right for more room to attack the ball from the inside.</p></li>
<li><p>It’s all in the hips. Initiate the downswing with your hips rotating first, which will drop the club on the inside.</p></li>
<li><p>Remember to have rock solid foundation. Maintain a central weight distribution throughout the shot to avoid sliding into the ball with an inconsistent swing path.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Don&rsquo;t get bogged down trying to correct that flying elbow or reverse pivot the next time things start to go south on the links. Simply look at the start line and shape of your shot to reveal everything about your swing and work backwards from there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who we are betting on in the Masters]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/12/who-we-are-betting-on-in-the-masters/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T21:48:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/12/who-we-are-betting-on-in-the-masters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/masters.jpg"></p>

<p>We’re coming up to the most iconic spectacle in golf and once again Tiger Woods is making the headlines for all the wrong reasons. Surgery on a pinched nerve in his back has forced him to withdraw from the tournament for the first time since 1994. Having withdrawn once and posting at least three of his highest scores ever this season, seeing him lift the trophy on Sunday would have been less than probable. However, unlike any other player on the PGA Tour, he gets the people going, as well as the advertising revenues – even when he’s on the second page of the leaderboard.</p>

<p>The last time Tiger missed the Masters, the western world went haywire. O.J. Simpson was arrested, the MLB World Series was cancelled, and Kurt Cobain was found dead. Are we heading for a similar set of circumstances this year?</p>

<p>The experts may be getting themselves all worked up regarding Tiger’s absence, but they are forgetting one simple fact. No player is bigger than the Masters itself. Augusta National will always be the star in this show while McIlroy, Mickelson, Day and Bubba adorn the list of potential suitors, and we all know what happens when Phil “turns up.” So the question is, will we see a clansman of the Tour or a millennial sporting the Green Jacket on Sunday?</p>

<p>Omitting Jimmy Walker for his amazing triple win season start, the latest batch of PGA winners have all limped and fumbled over the finishing line, leaving fans deservedly concerned and uninspired about the fate of 2014’s first major. World rankings and national qualifying tournaments play a much larger part in concocting the field for the Masters than regular PGA tournaments, so fret not, the majority of lackadaisical PGA millennials will not be making an appearance on this hallowed turf, leaving the door wide open for one of our old favorites.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/masters2.jpg"></p>

<p>Stenson, Mickelson, Day and McIlroy are all odds on favorites, but should we trust the experts? Mickelson is random at best, Stenson has questionable results at Augusta, and Day has just returned after a six week hiatus following wrist surgery. Taking this into consideration, we weigh up our options and share our top three Masters picks.</p>

<p>With two wins and five top 25s in his last 11 starts, Cedar Rapids local Zach Johnson is off to a dominant start. Plotting his way around methodically rather than bludgeoning the course has proven fruitful once before in 2007, plus a win going toe-to-toe against Tiger himself means he won’t be shaking in his cleats coming down the stretch on Sunday. With a 0.264 strokes gained putting stat and ranked 7th overall in scoring average, at 33-1 Zach is at the very least worth an each way bet.</p>

<p>McIlroy may be the bookies’ favorite thanks to his world rankings, but a timid start to the year has left a lot of people scratching their heads. McIlroy’s Masters chances rely on momentum from a solid performance at the Shell Houston Open and whether he can tame the short stick and improve his strokes gained putting statistic. If the planets align, the rain comes down, and his putter heats up, he could potentially overpower and dominate the field at Augusta. At 10-1 the pot won’t be huge, but it’s safe to say he’ll be in the top five.</p>

<p>Glancing over Kuchar’s PGA Tour stats may read like a lecture on Bell’s Normal Distribution curve, but, while he may not rank first in anything, every aspect of his game ranks on average in the top half. It doesn’t sound like the makeup of a champion, but it does mean he has no apparent weaknesses, a powerful attribute at Augusta. With a happy go lucky mindset and a strong showing at both the Valero Texas and Shell Houston Open, this could just be the warmup the Georgia Tech alumni needs at 18-1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two modern golf principles you need to know about]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/12/two-modern-golf-principles-you-need-to-know-about/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T21:47:40-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/12/two-modern-golf-principles-you-need-to-know-about</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Punctuated by high, weak, and disparaging shots, another routine weekend hack around the golf course can leave you in anguish. If you suffer from such afflictions, here are two modern golfing principles that can change the way you drive the ball.</p>

<p>Spin Loft</p>

<p>Are your approach shots consistently missing the mark? Low compression is a likely culprit. For decades, this axiom has been thrown around the game in an attempt to describe a player’s ball striking ability, based simply on subjective cues. But now in the age of launch monitors, compression has its own unit of measurement and a new name; it’s called spin loft, and is measured in degrees. It determines everything from smash factor, ball speed, spin rate, carry, and total distance, and now we can finally observe and harness it. This is clearly a stat to take note of.</p>

<p>Spin loft is the angle between two vectors: dynamic loft and angle of attack. It ultimately governs the amount of spin on the ball and the “obliqueness” of the strike. Fundamentally, more energy is transferred into propelling the ball forwards with a low angle of spin loft than a high one. It comes as no surprise to hear that top professionals and amateurs produce low figures of spin loft, but surely a few degrees can’t make that much difference, right?</p>

<p>Well, lets take two shots with a driver; we’ll negate shaft flex for simplicity and assume centered contact and a 100 mph club head speed. Shot one’s angle of attack is -5° and the dynamic loft is 15°, while shot two’s angle of attack is +10°, with a dynamic loft of 15°. Common sense suggests that the two shots should launch similarly with such comparable dynamic lofts, but with a 15° difference in spin loft, this isn’t the case. Shot one launches lower, producing higher spin, 20° of spin loft, and a ball speed of 140 mph, while shot two launches higher with less spin, 5° of spin loft and 149 mph ball speed. With an approximate gain of nine mph ball speed, those few degrees really do add up.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/golf-angle-diagram.png"></p>

<p>Lowering your spin loft is easier said than done, but getting yourself booked on a launch monitor and examining your dynamic loft and angle of attack is a good start. We recommend a fitting center at Roger Dunn from Worldwide Golf Shops. (Link: <a href="http://www.worldwidegolfshops.com/wwg-fitting-centers.html">http://www.worldwidegolfshops.com/wwg-fitting-centers.html</a> ) If nothing else, recognizing these concepts will help you understand the laws of ball flight better than your golfing buddies. For more information, check out this Trackman Smash Factor &amp; Spin Loft case study.</p>

<p>Vertical Gear Effect</p>

<p>Did you just buy a $500 adjustable driver? Are you still hitting it shorter than your friends? We have three words for you: vertical gear effect. No, this isn’t a rock climbing apparatus or the next big gaming release. It’s a phenomenon the golf industry has been taking advantage of ever since we saw the introduction of titanium driver heads, and it truly gives the weekend warrior something for nothing.</p>

<p>Without delving into face curvature and bulge, vertical gear effect is the rotation of the clubface around the center of gravity. When two gears work in unison, one gear travels in one direction and the secondary gear moves in the opposite direction. It’s the same principle when applied horizontally, which causes a hook off the toe and a slice off the heel. Comparably, striking the ball above the center of gravity causes the club to rotate clockwise; due to dynamic loft, our shot will never have topspin, but it will also have drastically less backspin, which means more mph, yards, and bragging rights.</p>

<p>For those with an adjustable driver, faster ball speeds could be just a screw turn away. Lower the center of gravity by adding a few extra grams to the sole of the club and aim for the top inch of the clubface.</p>

<p>For an in-depth look at vertical gear effect, check out Trackman Case Study #1.</p>

<p>So next time you’re out on the course, remember these principles and you’ll be smashing it past your buddies and feeling great about your game. Golf anguish? Not on this tee.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three golf gadgets to help you take control of your game]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/11/three-golf-gadgets-to-help-you-take-control-of-your-game/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-11T21:53:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/blog/2014/04/11/three-golf-gadgets-to-help-you-take-control-of-your-game</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three golf gadgets to help you take control of your game As tempting as it may be to spend your hard earned cash on one of the new adjustable drivers or a set of muscle-cavity-blade irons, the fact is whilst these may improve your golfing street credit, the will have little consequence on your game. Here are Teebox’s top 3 golfing gadgets to help you understand your swing mechanics and idiosyncrasies to lower your scores.</p>

<p><strong>Swingbyte 2</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/App-Device-med.jpg"></p>

<p>Whilst advances in club technology can make minor reductions to axis spin and increases in ball speed, the secret to pure golf shots lies in understanding how to apply the club correctly to the ball. Swingbyte 2 clips onto any club and aims to shed light on our own swing mechanics by wirelessly transmitting real-time swing data and interactive 3-D modeling to your iOS or Andriod device. They have made slip-free stability enhancements over the previous Swingbyte unit as well as a major overhaul of their app and online analytics software.</p>

<p>The device captures critical data on club head speed, angle of attack, face angle relative to path and dynamic loft at impact, which are the keys in fathoming and optimizing your ball flight. The Figures tracked have been verified alongside leading club tracking software to within a couple of degrees when calibrated properly so you can be confident of its aptitude. The ability to record quantifiable, consistent and objective data on what elements of your swing cause poor shots is imperative to becoming a better player. Swingbyte 2 retails at $149.99 + P&amp;P and is available to preorder online at <a href="https://www.swingbyte.com/store?product=2">https://www.swingbyte.com/store?product=2</a></p>

<p><strong>The Orange Stick Putting Aid</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/orange-stick.jpg"></p>

<p>Out of all the clubs in the bag, none has more consequence on your score than the putter. Whilst it is universally accepted that there is no right or wrong in putting, one thing in common with all the greats is a square face at impact. Doppler radar technology has confirmed that face angle at impact is the overriding factor in determining where the ball starts relative to our target.</p>

<p>The Orange Stick concentrates solely on this principle and provides instant and gratifying feedback on your face angle at impact. The aid has been designed for holing those problematic three footers, but you can also use it on anything up to twenty feet.</p>

<p>Place the Orange Stick three feet away from the hole and use the sightlines to align yourself and the putter face square to your target. Poor putts fall off the side immediately outlining any patterns in face angle with good putts sailing straight down the center. At $21.95 + P&amp;P this is the easiest and most inexpensive way to drop 3 shots of your score.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.getthestick.com/">http://www.getthestick.com/</a></p>

<p><strong>Bushnell V3 Rangefinder</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teeboxnetwork.com/images/bushnell-v3.jpg"></p>

<p>Markers and distances found on the course seldom bear any relevance to the actual distance you have to the pin. A back pin position may be as much as thirty yards out from the yardage declared on the scorecard.</p>

<p>GPS rangefinders give golfers accurate yardages to the center, front and back of the greens, however this often doesn’t tell the full story. Laser range finders offer yardages directly to the pin, but have always been plagued by the operators’ ability to discern whether they had indeed locked onto the target or a palm tree 40 yards over the back.</p>

<p>The latest offering from Bushnell seeks to remedy this. The V3 offers JOLT technology, which eliminates doubt by delivering a short vibrating burst to reinforce the laser has locked onto the flag. Hitting your approach shots pin high is paramount to eliminating 3 putts and lowering your score. The V3 is legal to use in tournament play and retails at $299.99 + P&amp;P with its non-legal V3 Slope counterpart at $399.99 + P&amp;P. To find out more go to <a href="http://bushnellgolf.com/laser/tourv3.cfm">http://bushnellgolf.com/laser/tourv3.cfm</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
