<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Teebox blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://dodgerogers.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dodgerogers.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-12T23:04:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://dodgerogers.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Teebox]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who we are betting on in the Masters]]></title>
    <link href="http://dodgerogers.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/who-we-are-betting-on-in-the-masters/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T21:48:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dodgerogers.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/who-we-are-betting-on-in-the-masters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://dodgerogers.github.io/images/masters.jpg"></p>

<p>We’re coming up to the most iconic spectacle in golf and once again Tiger Woods is making the headlines for all the wrong reasons. Surgery on a pinched nerve in his back has forced him to withdraw from the tournament for the first time since 1994. Having withdrawn once and posting at least three of his highest scores ever this season, seeing him lift the trophy on Sunday would have been less than probable. However, unlike any other player on the PGA Tour, he gets the people going, as well as the advertising revenues – even when he’s on the second page of the leaderboard.</p>

<p>The last time Tiger missed the Masters, the western world went haywire. O.J. Simpson was arrested, the MLB World Series was cancelled, and Kurt Cobain was found dead. Are we heading for a similar set of circumstances this year?</p>

<p>The experts may be getting themselves all worked up regarding Tiger’s absence, but they are forgetting one simple fact. No player is bigger than the Masters itself. Augusta National will always be the star in this show while McIlroy, Mickelson, Day and Bubba adorn the list of potential suitors, and we all know what happens when Phil “turns up.” So the question is, will we see a clansman of the Tour or a millennial sporting the Green Jacket on Sunday?</p>

<p>Omitting Jimmy Walker for his amazing triple win season start, the latest batch of PGA winners have all limped and fumbled over the finishing line, leaving fans deservedly concerned and uninspired about the fate of 2014’s first major. World rankings and national qualifying tournaments play a much larger part in concocting the field for the Masters than regular PGA tournaments, so fret not, the majority of lackadaisical PGA millennials will not be making an appearance on this hallowed turf, leaving the door wide open for one of our old favorites.</p>

<p><img src="http://dodgerogers.github.io/images/masters2.jpg"></p>

<p>Stenson, Mickelson, Day and McIlroy are all odds on favorites, but should we trust the experts? Mickelson is random at best, Stenson has questionable results at Augusta, and Day has just returned after a six week hiatus following wrist surgery. Taking this into consideration, we weigh up our options and share our top three Masters picks.</p>

<p>With two wins and five top 25s in his last 11 starts, Cedar Rapids local Zach Johnson is off to a dominant start. Plotting his way around methodically rather than bludgeoning the course has proven fruitful once before in 2007, plus a win going toe-to-toe against Tiger himself means he won’t be shaking in his cleats coming down the stretch on Sunday. With a 0.264 strokes gained putting stat and ranked 7th overall in scoring average, at 33-1 Zach is at the very least worth an each way bet.</p>

<p>McIlroy may be the bookies’ favorite thanks to his world rankings, but a timid start to the year has left a lot of people scratching their heads. McIlroy’s Masters chances rely on momentum from a solid performance at the Shell Houston Open and whether he can tame the short stick and improve his strokes gained putting statistic. If the planets align, the rain comes down, and his putter heats up, he could potentially overpower and dominate the field at Augusta. At 10-1 the pot won’t be huge, but it’s safe to say he’ll be in the top five.</p>

<p>Glancing over Kuchar’s PGA Tour stats may read like a lecture on Bell’s Normal Distribution curve, but, while he may not rank first in anything, every aspect of his game ranks on average in the top half. It doesn’t sound like the makeup of a champion, but it does mean he has no apparent weaknesses, a powerful attribute at Augusta. With a happy go lucky mindset and a strong showing at both the Valero Texas and Shell Houston Open, this could just be the warmup the Georgia Tech alumni needs at 18-1.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two modern golf principles you need to know about]]></title>
    <link href="http://dodgerogers.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/two-modern-golf-principles-you-need-to-know-about/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-12T21:47:40-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://dodgerogers.github.io/blog/2014/04/12/two-modern-golf-principles-you-need-to-know-about</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Punctuated by high, weak, and disparaging shots, another routine weekend hack around the golf course can leave you in anguish. If you suffer from such afflictions, here are two modern golfing principles that can change the way you drive the ball.</p>

<p>Spin Loft</p>

<p>Are your approach shots consistently missing the mark? Low compression is a likely culprit. For decades, this axiom has been thrown around the game in an attempt to describe a player’s ball striking ability, based simply on subjective cues. But now in the age of launch monitors, compression has its own unit of measurement and a new name; it’s called spin loft, and is measured in degrees. It determines everything from smash factor, ball speed, spin rate, carry, and total distance, and now we can finally observe and harness it. This is clearly a stat to take note of.</p>

<p>Spin loft is the angle between two vectors: dynamic loft and angle of attack. It ultimately governs the amount of spin on the ball and the “obliqueness” of the strike. Fundamentally, more energy is transferred into propelling the ball forwards with a low angle of spin loft than a high one. It comes as no surprise to hear that top professionals and amateurs produce low figures of spin loft, but surely a few degrees can’t make that much difference, right?</p>

<p>Well, lets take two shots with a driver; we’ll negate shaft flex for simplicity and assume centered contact and a 100 mph club head speed. Shot one’s angle of attack is -5° and the dynamic loft is 15°, while shot two’s angle of attack is +10°, with a dynamic loft of 15°. Common sense suggests that the two shots should launch similarly with such comparable dynamic lofts, but with a 15° difference in spin loft, this isn’t the case. Shot one launches lower, producing higher spin, 20° of spin loft, and a ball speed of 140 mph, while shot two launches higher with less spin, 5° of spin loft and 149 mph ball speed. With an approximate gain of nine mph ball speed, those few degrees really do add up.</p>

<p><img src="http://dodgerogers.github.io/images/golf-angle-diagram.png"></p>

<p>Lowering your spin loft is easier said than done, but getting yourself booked on a launch monitor and examining your dynamic loft and angle of attack is a good start. We recommend a fitting center at Roger Dunn from Worldwide Golf Shops. (Link: <a href="http://www.worldwidegolfshops.com/wwg-fitting-centers.html">http://www.worldwidegolfshops.com/wwg-fitting-centers.html</a> ) If nothing else, recognizing these concepts will help you understand the laws of ball flight better than your golfing buddies. For more information, check out this Trackman Smash Factor &amp; Spin Loft case study.</p>

<p>Vertical Gear Effect</p>

<p>Did you just buy a $500 adjustable driver? Are you still hitting it shorter than your friends? We have three words for you: vertical gear effect. No, this isn’t a rock climbing apparatus or the next big gaming release. It’s a phenomenon the golf industry has been taking advantage of ever since we saw the introduction of titanium driver heads, and it truly gives the weekend warrior something for nothing.</p>

<p>Without delving into face curvature and bulge, vertical gear effect is the rotation of the clubface around the center of gravity. When two gears work in unison, one gear travels in one direction and the secondary gear moves in the opposite direction. It’s the same principle when applied horizontally, which causes a hook off the toe and a slice off the heel. Comparably, striking the ball above the center of gravity causes the club to rotate clockwise; due to dynamic loft, our shot will never have topspin, but it will also have drastically less backspin, which means more mph, yards, and bragging rights.</p>

<p>For those with an adjustable driver, faster ball speeds could be just a screw turn away. Lower the center of gravity by adding a few extra grams to the sole of the club and aim for the top inch of the clubface.</p>

<p>For an in-depth look at vertical gear effect, check out Trackman Case Study #1.</p>

<p>So next time you’re out on the course, remember these principles and you’ll be smashing it past your buddies and feeling great about your game. Golf anguish? Not on this tee.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
